export const GEOGRAPHYA2015 = [

{
id: "question1",
question:  "1. What is the scale of the map in statement form?",
A: "One centimetre on the map represents half a kilometre on the ground",
B: "One centimetre on the map represents one and a half kilometres on the ground",
C: "One centimetre on the map represents two kilometres on the ground",
D: "One centimetre on the map represents four kilometres on the ground",
answer: "A. One centimetre on the map represents half a kilometre on the ground",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question2",
question:  "2. What is the approximate distance as a crow flies from Mami to Esho?",
A: "12.0 km",
B: "9.0 km",
C: "3.0km",
D: "1.5 km",
answer: "A. 12.0 km",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question3",
question:  "3. Which of the following settlements performs an administrative function?",
A: "Jaba",
B: "Ede",
C: "BUTO",
D: "Ititi",
answer: "C. BUTO",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question5",
question:  "5. What is the direction of flow of River Afikpo?",
A: "Southwest",
B: "Northeast",
C: "Northwest",
D: "Southeast",
answer: "C. Northwest",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question7",
question:  "7. What is the contour interval of the map?",
A: "25 metres",
B: "50 metres",
C: "100 metres",
D: "150 metres",
answer: "C. 100 metres",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question8",
question:  "8. Which economic activity could be practised in the south-eastern part of the mapped area?",
A: "Animal rearing",
B: "Lumbering",
C: "Trading",
D: "Mining",
answer: "A. Animal rearing",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question9",
question:  "9. Which of the following modes of transport is commonly used in the mapped area?",
A: "River",
B: "Road",
C: "Rail",
D: "Air",
answer: "B. Road",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question10",
question:  "10. The distance by road from Mami to BUTO is approximately",
A: "9.0 km",
B: "14.0 km",
C: "23.0 km",
D: "25.0 km",
answer: "A. 9.0 km",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question4",
question:  "4. In which part of the mapped area is lumbering a likely economic activity?",
A: "Northeast",
B: "Southeast",
C: "Southwest",
D: "northwest",
answer: "D. northwest",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question6",
question:  "6. What is the settlement pattern of Ede?",
A: "Isolated",
B: "Dispersed",
C: "Annular",
D: "Linear",
answer: "D. Linear",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question11",
question:  "11. The hottest planet is",
A: "Venus",
B: "Pluto",
C: "Mercury",
D: "Jupiter",
answer: "A. Venus",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question12",
question:  "12. When does the eclipse of the moon occur?",
A: "When the earth comes between the sun and the moon",
B: "Whenever the earth rotates through 3600",
C: "When the sun comes between the moon and the earth",
D: "When the earth completes a revolution",
answer: "A. When the earth comes between the sun and the moon",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question13",
question:  "13. The upfolded part of a fold mountain is called",
A: "Sial",
B: "Anticline",
C: "Syncline",
D: "Sill",
answer: "B. Anticline",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question14",
question:  "14. The part of the earth’s crust which is made up of silica and alumina is the",
A: "Sima",
B: "Mantle",
C: "Barysphere",
D: "Sial.",
answer: "D. Sial.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question15",
question:  "15. During equinox,",
A: "The Tropic of Cancer experiences a longer day than the Tropic of Capricorn.",
B: "All places across the globe experience an equal length of day and night.",
C: "The length of the day at the Equator is shorter than at the Tropic of Cancer.",
D: "The moon is star-shaped all through the night all over the world.",
answer: "B. All places across the globe experience an equal length of day and night.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question16",
question:  "16. Whenever volcanic eruption occurs,",
A: "A new flat surface emerges.",
B: "Residual mountains are formed.",
C: "Overthrust IbId is formed.",
D: "Gases and molten magma are ejected.",
answer: "D. Gases and molten magma are ejected.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question17",
question:  "17. The extent of coastal erosion depends on the",
A: "Amount of fresh water supplied by tributaries.",
B: "Depth of ocean water.",
C: "Salinity of the ocean.",
D: "Nature of the waves.",
answer: "D. Nature of the waves.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question18",
question:  "18. Which of the following is a characteristic of igneous rock?",
A: "Loose in composition",
B: "Arranged in layers",
C: "Crystalline in nature",
D: "Porous in granular structure",
answer: "C. Crystalline in nature",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question19",
question:  "19. The temperature at the foot of a mountain is 20°C. If the mountain is 6000 metres above sea level, what will be the temperature at the top of the mountain?",
A: "-19°C",
B: "-16°C",
C: "14°C",
D: "19°C",
answer: "A. -19°C",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question20",
question:  "20. Wind erosion is common in arid areas because",
A: "Rains are widespread and long lasting",
B: "Wind speed is high and there are few wind breaks",
C: "Pressure falls below normal in desert areas.",
D: "The rocks are resistant to heat.",
answer: "B. Wind speed is high and there are few wind breaks",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question21",
question:  "21. Which of the following features could be found in the upper course of rivers?",
A: "Ox-bow lakes",
B: "Waterfalls",
C: "Deltas",
D: "Levees",
answer: "B. Waterfalls",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question22",
question:  "22. Ash and cinder cones are associated with",
A: "Ozone depletion.",
B: "Hurricane’s activities.",
C: "Earthquakes.",
D: "Volcanic eruption.",
answer: "D. Volcanic eruption.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question23",
question:  "23. Deposition of fine-grained sand carried over long distance by wind is known as",
A: "Chernozem.",
B: "Laterite.",
C: "Loess.",
D: "Podzol.",
answer: "C. Loess.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question24",
question:  "24. The core of the earth is called",
A: "Mesosphere.",
B: "Lithosphere.",
C: "Hydrosphere.",
D: "Barysphere.",
answer: "D. Barysphere.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question25",
question:  "25. Which of the following environmental resources is non-renewable?",
A: "Rain",
B: "Minerals",
C: "Water",
D: "Oxygen",
answer: "B. Minerals",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question26",
question:  "26. Relief rainfall is common around the",
A: "Lowland areas.",
B: "Peneplains.",
C: "Highland areas.",
D: "Sahara Desert.",
answer: "C. Highland areas.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question27",
question:  "27. Which of the following features is of volcanic origin?",
A: "Sill",
B: "Zeugen",
C: "Loess",
D: "Gorge",
answer: "A. Sill",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question28",
question:  "28. The instrument used in measuring atmospheric pressure is",
A: "Hygrometer.",
B: "Barometer.",
C: "Thermometer.",
D: "Anemometer.",
answer: "B. Barometer.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question29",
question:  "29. The gradual breakdown of rocks in situ by either physical or chemical process is called",
A: "Erosion.",
B: "Denudation.",
C: "Weathering.",
D: "Deposition.",
answer: "C. Weathering.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question30",
question:  "30. The fourth planet from the sun in the solar system is",
A: "Mercury",
B: "Uranus.",
C: "Neptune",
D: "Mars.",
answer: "D. Mars.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question31",
question:  "31. Which rock type involves stratification?",
A: "Metamorphic",
B: "Sedimentary.",
C: "Volcanic",
D: "Igneous",
answer: "B. Sedimentary.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question32",
question:  "32. Which type of rainfall occurs when two air masses of different temperatures and other physical properties meet?",
A: "Orographic rainfall",
B: "Relief rainfall",
C: "Cyclonical rainfall",
D: "Convectional rainfall -",
answer: "C. Cyclonical rainfall",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question33",
question:  "33. In what regions can stalactites, swallow holes and caverns be found?",
A: "Plateau regions",
B: "Coastal regions",
C: "Mountainous regions",
D: "Limestone regions",
answer: "D. Limestone regions",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question34",
question:  "34. The remains of eroded highLand in desert and semi-desert environments are commonly called",
A: "Self dunes.",
B: "Barchans.",
C: "lnselbergs.",
D: "Volcanic plug.",
answer: "C. lnselbergs.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question35",
question:  "35. The time in town X on longitude 150 E is 4.00 pm. What will be the time in town Y on longitude 150 W?",
A: "2.00 am",
B: "2.00 pm",
C: "6.00 pm",
D: "6.00 am",
answer: "B. 2.00 pm",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question36",
question:  "36. Which of the following is an advantage of solar energy over other sources of energy?",
A: "It is easily renewable",
B: "It requires physical gradient difference",
C: "The demand for it comes from specialized agencies.",
D: "Its waste is difficult to manage.",
answer: "A. It is easily renewable",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question37",
question:  "37. One relative advantage of water transport over road transport is its",
A: "Great speed over long distances.",
B: "Capacity for carrying bulky goods.",
C: "Ability to link all parts of a country.",
D: "Ability to withstand bad weather.",
answer: "B. Capacity for carrying bulky goods.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question38",
question:  "38. The number of people living in a unit area of land is termed its",
A: "Birth rate.",
B: "Death rate.",
C: "Dependency ratio.",
D: "Population density.",
answer: "D. Population density.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question39",
question:  "39. An effect of rural-urban migration on the source region is",
A: "Rural depopulation.",
B: "Urban depopulalion.",
C: "Rural employment.",
D: "Rural unemployment.",
answer: "A. Rural depopulation.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question40",
question:  "40. Which of the following best explains high rate of population growth in West Africa?",
A: "Birth control policies",
B: "High birth rate and low death rate",
C: "Low birth rate and high death rate",
D: "High rate of immigration",
answer: "A. Birth control policies",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question41",
question:  "41. Which of the following distinguishes heavy industries from light industries?",
A: "Complexities of processing techniques",
B: "Amount of waste products generated",
C: "Ownership structure of the firm",
D: "Source of raw materials",
answer: "A. Complexities of processing techniques",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question42",
question:  "42. The cheapest mode of transport for the conveyance of bulky goods is",
A: "Air.",
B: "Land.",
C: "Pipeline.",
D: "Water.",
answer: "D. Water.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question43",
question:  "43. The major trading partners of the Anglophone West African countries are",
A: "Britain. U.S.A, Germany and Japan.",
B: "Germany, China, South Africa and Norway",
C: "Belgium, India, Columbia and Chile.",
D: "Chile, Pakistan, Japan and Britain.",
answer: "A. Britain. U.S.A, Germany and Japan.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question44",
question:  "44. Which of the following is true of inter-community relationships?",
A: "Females migrate to rural areas to give birth",
B: "Youth migrate to urban areas in search of jobs",
C: "Immigrants settle in the city’s central business district",
D: "City dwellers seek schools for their children in rural areas.",
answer: "B. Youth migrate to urban areas in search of jobs",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question45",
question:  "45. If a country has a population of 20,000,000 and its size is 1,000,000 km2, then its population density is",
A: "5 persons/km2",
B: "15 persons/km2",
C: "20 persons/km2",
D: "30 persons/km2",
answer: "C. 20 persons/km2",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question46",
question:  "46. Which of the following criteria is not important in distinguishing between a village and a town?",
A: "Geographical situation",
B: "Population size",
C: "Range of functions",
D: "Variety of activities",
answer: "A. Geographical situation",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question47",
question:  "47. One of the usefulness of import tariff on imported goods is the",
A: "Encouragement of importation from abroad.",
B: "Multiplication of foreign goods in local markets.",
C: "Protection of infant industries.",
D: "Saving money in foreign accounts.",
answer: "C. Protection of infant industries.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question48",
question:  "48. One of the problems limiting the achievement of the objectives of the Economic Community of West African States is",
A: "The use of common currency.",
B: "Strong colonial ties.",
C: "Climatic differences.",
D: "Similarity in language.",
answer: "B. Strong colonial ties.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question49",
question:  "49. Cattle ranching is not common in the forest regions of West Africa because of the",
A: "Scarcity of grass for fodder.",
B: "Presence of tsetse flies.",
C: "Absence of Fulani herdsmen.",
D: "Presence of wildlife.",
answer: "B. Presence of tsetse flies._",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question50",
question:  "50. The location of market gardening near large cities is best explained by",
A: "Availability of power.",
B: "Fertile soil.",
C: "Perishability of products.",
D: "Efficient transportation.",
answer: "C. Perishability of products.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},


]